<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>algos on Prasanna</title>
    <link>/categories/algos/</link>
    <description>Recent content in algos on Prasanna</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/algos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Algo walkthrough: number of islands</title>
      <link>/posts/20201125100541-algo_walkthrough_number_of_islands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20201125100541-algo_walkthrough_number_of_islands/</guid>
      <description>The problem  Given an m x n 2d grid map of &amp;lsquo;1&amp;rsquo;s (land) and &amp;lsquo;0&amp;rsquo;s (water), return the number of islands. An island is surrounded by water and is formed by connecting adjacent lands horizontally or vertically. You may assume all four edges of the grid are all surrounded by water.
 Exploration The first instinct is to lower the dimension of the problem and see what that looks like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algo walkthrough: longest sequence in unsorted array</title>
      <link>/posts/20201123210516-algo_walkthrough_longest_sequence_in_unsorted_array/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20201123210516-algo_walkthrough_longest_sequence_in_unsorted_array/</guid>
      <description>The setup We have an unsorted array. It may or may not have a sequence of numbers. We have to find the length of the longest sequence.
Hints  They hint at a \(O(n)\) solution. This can be useful at a later point. They also say the length of the array can be between \(1, 10000\). This means we can a small array of size \(10\) and manually try out solutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algo walkthrough: swapping elements to find max score</title>
      <link>/posts/20201122105230-algo_walkthrough_swapping_elements_to_find_max_score/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20201122105230-algo_walkthrough_swapping_elements_to_find_max_score/</guid>
      <description>Problem statement Given an array of size \(n\), the beauty of this array is defined as sum of \(abs(index-value)\) for each element. Swapping two elements of this array, what is the maximum beauty possible?
Initial setup The initial setup consists of an unsorted array. Each element has a score defined as the absolute value of the difference the element&amp;rsquo;s value and its index.
The absolute value The metric for each element gives us a sense of displacement.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>